<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A right fruitfull admonition concerning the order of a good Christian mans life very profitable for all maner of estates, and other to beholde and looke vppon / made by the famouse doctour Collet, sometime deane of Paules.</title>
            <author>Colet, John, 1467?-1519.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5549.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4589</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23593052</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23593052</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19140)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1830:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A right fruitfull admonition concerning the order of a good Christian mans life very profitable for all maner of estates, and other to beholde and looke vppon / made by the famouse doctour Collet, sometime deane of Paules.</title>
                  <author>Colet, John, 1467?-1519.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Gabriell Cawood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The order of a good Christian mans life.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Magdalene College (University of  Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26750:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RIGHT FRVIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full admonition, concerning the order of a good Chriſtian mans life, <hi>very profitable for all maner of Eſtates, and other to beholde and looke vppon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by the famous Doctour</hi> Collet, <hi>ſometime deane of Paules.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London for Gabriell Cawood. 1582.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="warning">
            <pb facs="tcp:26750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26750:2"/>
            <head>A fruitfull monition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the order of a good Chriſtian mans life, very profitable for all maner of <hi>Eſates and</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to beholde and looke vppon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emember firſt of all (vertuous reder) that it is high wiſedome &amp; great perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thy ſelfe to know, and then thy ſelfe to deſpiſe. Thou muſt knowe that thou haſt nothing that good is of thy ſelfe, but of God: For the gifts of nature, &amp; al other tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral giftes of this world, which be lawfully and truely obtained, well conſidered, beene come to thee by the infinite goodneſſe and grace of God, and not of thy ſelfe. But in eſpecial it is neceſſarie <pb facs="tcp:26750:3"/>for thee to knowe that God of his great grace hath made thee his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, hauing regarde to thy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, vnderſtanding, and free will, and that God is thy maker, &amp; thou his wretched creature, &amp; that thou art redeemed of God by the paſſion of Chriſt Ieſu, and that God is thy helper. thy refuge, and thy deliuerer from all euil, and to conſider and knowe the goodly order which God of his infinite wiſedome hath orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thee to be ordered by. As to haue theſe temporal goodes for the neceſſitie of thy body: the body and ſenſual appetites to be ordered by thy ſoule: thy ſoule to be ordred by reaſon &amp; grace: by reaſon and grace to knowe thy duetie to God and to thy neighbour, and by all common reaſon if thou kepe this conuenient order to God and his creatures, they ſhall keepe their order to thee:
<pb facs="tcp:26750:3"/>But if thou breake thine order to them, of likely hood they ſhal breake their order to thee. For how ſhould thy wife, children, ſeruaunts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, with the which thou haſt dooings, doo their dutie, and kepe their order to thee, if thou doeſt not ſo to God and to them? And alſo thinke thou of a ſuretie, that if thy ſenſuall apetite be not ordred by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and grace, thou art worſe ordred than a beaſt: for then thou liueſt out of order, &amp; ſo doth not a beaſt, which is a great ſhame and rebuke to thee a reaſonable creature, and without the great mercie of God, it ſhalbe to thine eternal damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thinke and thanke God, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſſpiſe thy ſelfe, and thinke thy ſelfe a great wretch, in that God hath done ſo much for thee, and thou haſt ſo oft offended his highneſſe, &amp; alſo done him ſo litle ſeruice. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb facs="tcp:26750:4"/>it is alſo great wiſedom to think, that if it had pleaſd God for to haue giuen to all other men (aſwell beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers as other) like grace as he hath giuen to thee, that they would haue ſerued his goodnes better than thy ſelfe haſt don: Wherefore thinke thy ſelfe a wretch of al wretches, except the mercy of God. And therefore by his infinite mercy and grace, call vnto thy remembraunce the degree or dignitie which almightie God of his goodnes hath called thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and according thereunto yeelde thy debt, and doo thy duetie.</p>
            <p>¶ Firſt and principally, honour God as thy maker, loue him as thy redeemer, feare him as thy iudge. Secondarily, thy neighbour which is thy ſuperiour, obey: Haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and peace with them which be euen with thee in degree: &amp; haue mercy and pity on thine inferiours
<pb facs="tcp:26750:4"/>Thirdly, prouide thee to haue a cleane heart, and a good cuſtodie of thy toong. Pray and take labor by grace to haue wiſedome &amp; cunning to do thy duetie to God and to thy neighbour. And in all thy words &amp; dedes haue euer in minde, that God and his angels heareth and ſeeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie thing, and that nothing is ſo priuily done, but it ſhal be made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. And in eſpecial haue in minde that thou ſhalt die ſhortly, and how Chriſt died for thee, the ſubtilty and falſenes of this temporal world, the ioyes of heauen, and the paines of hell. And euery morning, among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy meditations and prayers, pray vnto thy Lord God, that the day folowing, thou (acording to the degree which he of his infinite goodneſſe and mercie hath called thee vnto) maieſt vſe this temporall wretched world in thy thaughtes <pb facs="tcp:26750:5"/>words, and deedes, that by them and the merite of Chriſtes paſſion, thou maieſt eſchewe the paines of hel, and come to the ioy euerlaſting. And in executing thereof kepe truth in wordes and deedes. Defende no man, nor no matter, againſt the trueth. In all thinges thinke and truſt in God, and he ſhal direct thy wayes. Truſt not to thine owne witte, but feare God, and he will keepe thee from euil. If thou truſt more in thine owne witte than in the grace of God, thy policie ſhall be ſoone ſubuerted. Be content to heare good counſayle, though it be contrarie to thy will: For he is a verie foole that will heare nothing gladlie, but that is according to his mind. Do thou no man harme, leaſt thou ſuffereſt the ſame. As thou wouldeſt be done vnto, ſo do thou vnto other. Be ſuch to other, <pb facs="tcp:26750:5"/>as thou deſireſt they ſhould be to thee. If thou be religious, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that the due execution of true religion is not in wearing of the habite, but with a cleane mynde in verie deede to execute the rules and ordinances of religion: For ſo it is, that to weare the habite and not to execute the rule and order of religion, is rather to be deemed hipocriſie, or apoſtataſie, than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. If thou be lay and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried, keepe thee cleane vnto the time thou be maried. And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the ſore and terrible puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of
<hi>Noys</hi> flood, and of the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible fire and brimſtone &amp; ſore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmente of Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, done to man for miſuſing of the fleſhe. And in eſpecial ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l to remembrance the marueilous and horrible puniſhmente of that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable great pocks daiely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing <pb facs="tcp:26750:6"/>to our ſightes, groing in &amp; vpon mans fleſh, the which ſore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment (euerie thing wel remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred) cannot be thought, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for the inordinate miſuſe of to fleſhe. And if thou intende to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or be maried, and haſt a good wife, thanke our Lorde therefore, for ſhee is of his ſending. Ane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that three thieges in eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall beene pleaſaunt to the ſpirite of God, that is to ſay, concorde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene brethren, loue and charitie betwene neighbours, and a man &amp; his wife wel agreeing. And if thou haue an euil wife, take pacience, &amp; thanke God, for all is for the beſt, well taken: How be it thou art bounde to doo and praie for her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement, leaſt ſhee go to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, from whom ſhe came. And haue in remembraunce, that the intent of mariage is not in the beaſtly apetite <pb facs="tcp:26750:6"/>or pleaſure in the thing, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent there of is, to eſchewe the ſinne of the fleſh, or elſe to haue children. And if thou haue children, as much as thou mayeſt bring them vp in vertue, to be the ſeruaunts of God: for it is better for thee and them not to be borne, than to be other wiſe. In thine aucthoritie, buſie thee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be beloued of thine infery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, than to be dreaded. Let thy ſubiectes and ſeruauntes rather ſerue and obey thee for loue, than for dreade or neede: With ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne goodneſſe gouerne thy ſubiectes, that they may be glad to ſerue thee both in puniſhing and in cheriſhing.</p>
            <p>Keepe a manerly meane. Be not to ſtraite. Forgiue not to ſoon. Keep a conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t meſure in al thy works Go not to meate as a beaſt, but as a eaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>able man, ſay thy grace, &amp; then
<pb facs="tcp:26750:7"/>remenber that mo be ſicke and die by ſuperfluities of meates, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. Wherefore eate with meaſure, to liue in health. at thy meate haue none other but honeſt communication, and ſuch as is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy cunning. Backbite no man. Be merie in honeſtie: For ſorrow and care hath killed many, and no profite therein. In no wiſe ſweare, without compulſion of the lawe: For whereas is great ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence is neuer the plague of God. In no wiſe braul, ne chyde without an vrgent cauſe: For Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomon ſayth, better is a little with ioye, than a houſe ful of vitailes with brawling. Alſo he ſayth, An euil perſon is euer chyding, and therefore the Angell of God ſhall be ſent againſt him. Be content at thy dinner, &amp; alſo at other times to geue part of that which God <pb facs="tcp:26750:7"/>hath ſent thee: For he that wil not heare the cry of a poore man, he ſhal cry to God, and not be heard. After thy meat thanke God of that he hath ſent thee, or els thou doſt not as a reaſonable man, but like a beaſt, which in eating remembreth nothing but his meate. With good prouidence and diſcretion ſee thee time where, when, how, why, or wherefore thou ſpeakeſt, doeſt, or byddeſt any thing to be don. When thou deemeſt or iudgeſt any, be he poore or riche, behold and conſider the cauſe, and not the perſon. Be as meeke in other mens cauſes and offences, as in thine own. Sit ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in dome and iudgement with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pitie or mercy. For while thou haſt pitie, and art mercifull to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens offences, thou haſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on thy ſelfe: For in what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thou meaſureſt, it ſhal be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſured
<pb facs="tcp:26750:8"/>to thee. Yet thou muſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgemente, but it muſt be with pitie or mercy: For (of a ſuretie) to do mercie &amp; iuſtice, is more pleaſaunt to God, then to pray or to doo ſacrifice vnto him. Deeme no man by light ſuſpections. Firſt prone, and then deeme. In doubtes, reſerue the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to Gods might. That thou knoweſt not, commit it to God. haue litle or none affection &amp; loue to theſe earthlie and temporall thinges.</p>
            <p>For bleſſed is the riche man that truſteth not in his money and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Remember, as a man loueth ſo he is: For the louer is in the thing loued more properlie, than in him ſelfe. Wherefore, if a man loue earthlie thinges, he may be called, an earthly man. And if he loue prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie heauenlie thinges or God, he may be called, An heauenty or a Godly man. And therefore loue God <pb facs="tcp:26750:8"/>and heauenly thinges, for vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly that is beſt and moſt aſſured loue, for they be and euer ſhall be permanente, and all earthly things be ſoone vaniſhed and ended, and ſo the loue of them is in vaine. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is wiſedome to feare God: For as he ſayeth him ſelfe. Feare not him that may kill the bodie, and can not hurt the ſoule: but feare him that can kill the bodie and alſo the ſoule, and commit them to euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting paine. Wherefore, euery eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ere thou go to bed, cal to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce (as much as thou canſt) thy thoughtes, words, and deedes, ſayd and don that day. And if any haue been to thine owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and to the pleaſure of God, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily thanke him, for by his grace it was done. And if any haue beene contrarie to his pleaſure, aſke har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily mercy and reconcile thy ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:26750:9"/>ſhortly by repentaunce, to eſchewe the euerlaſting and terrible paines of hel. For (as
<hi>Saint-Auſtine</hi> ſayth) there is not a greater madneſſ, than for a little temporal delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which is ſoone done) to loſe the eternall ioye, and to be bounde to euerlaſting paine: from the which the almightie Father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by his infinite power and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and bitter paſſion and infinite wiſdome of Ieſu Chriſt, and by the infinite goodnes and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the holy Ghoſt keepe vs. Amen. <hi>Deo gracias.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vſe well tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral thinges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deſire eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal thinges.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
